Guide to the P. Adem Carroll Papers 1964-2018 (bulk, 2000-2010) MS 3212
New-York Historical Society
P. Adem Carroll papers
1964-2018 (Bulk 2000-2010)
New-York Historical Society
Carroll, P. Adem (Paul Adem)
MS 3212
11 Linear feet in 11 boxes (6 record cartons and 5 oversize cartons)
4.52 Gigabytes (10 files, including 8 WAV audio files that total approximately 2 hours in duration)
The collection consists of the professional and personal records of Paul Adem Carroll, a New York City-based Irish-American Muslim. Carroll's career tracks multiple decades of advocacy and activism on behalf of Muslims internationally and domestically, chief among which includes the detailed case files of some of the post-9/11 detainees and families for whom he provided legal and financial relief. Other subject areas include his founding and running of the Muslim Community Network (MCN), work with other New York City-area non-profits, various materials relating to Islam, and personal records.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series that reflects the work Carroll performed over his years as a community advocate and organizer:
Series I. Detainee Files, 1998-2011
Series II. Subject Files, 1964-2018
Series III. Publications, 1988-2010
Series IV. Audiovisual, 2002-2015
Series V. Artifacts, 2015
Biographical / Historical
Paul Adem Carroll (often referred to as P. Adem Carroll) is a New York City-based Irish-American Muslim, who has performed extensive advocacy for other Muslims domestically and internationally. Carroll graduated from Fiorello LaGuardia High School in 1975, after which he attended Bard College. After graduating in 1979, Carroll joined the Peace Corps, living in Marrakesh, Morocco, between 1980 and 1982. After returning to the United States, Carroll received his Masters' degree in Near and Middle Eastern Studies from New York University in 1987.
Carroll's work has largely focused on human rights advocacy, largely through non-governmental organizations. In the 1990s, Carroll worked for both Amnesty International and the Church Avenue Merchants Block Association, a Brooklyn-based nonprofit through Americorps. In 2001, Carroll joined the Islamic Circle of North America (ICNA) Relief, a Muslim grassroots organization that "seeks to alleviate human suffering by providing caring and compassionate service to victims of adversities and survivors of disasters." In his role as 9/11 Disaster Response Coordinator, Carroll provided emergency legal and financial assistance to over 800 detainees and their families in the wake of the attacks of September 11, 2001. Additionally, Carroll secured funding from the Rockefeller Foundation, which enabled his work to encompass so many detainees from across the United States. He left ICNA Relief in 2006.
In 2003, Carroll founded the Muslim Consultative Network (MCN; today the Muslim Community Network), a nonprofit organization that provided community education and leadership development opportunities to Muslim and immigrant communities. As Executive Director, Carroll oversaw a series of programs to meet the needs of New York City's Muslim community, such as with the Nafis Salaam anti-smoking program.
Although he left MCN formally in 2010, Carroll continued to perform important advocacy work for immigrants, refugees, and Muslims worldwide in various forms. Between 2004 and 2015, Carroll produced the "War on Immigrants Report," a monthly program that investigated American immigration policy and its effect on immigrants. He also published editorials in various Muslim publications, such as Muslims Weekly, Weekly Mirror, The Tri-State Muslim, and Islamic Monthly. Since 2013, Carroll worked as the Director of the Burma Task Force, a non-profit that advocates in close collaboration with the United Nations for the rights of the Rohingya Muslims and the end to genocide in Myanmar.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of P. Adem Carroll, 2021.
Scope and Contents
The P. Adem Carroll Papers includes documents from his work with post-9/11 detainees, as well as other files from his personal and professional life ranging from 1964 until 2018.
Series I. Detainee Files: The series consists of case files, arranged alphabetically by surname, of the post-9/11 detainees for whom Carroll provided legal and financial relief during his time at the ICNA Relief. These files include legal documents such as appeals, briefs, court stenographer's notes; correspondence, often with lawyers, politicians, judges, the detainees, or family members of the detainees; and financial documents, such as bills, invoices, checks, and other documents. Additionally, many of Carroll's professional documents that deal directly with detainees (detainee lists, handwritten notes, contact information, intake forms, among others) are included in the series.
Series II. Subject Files: The series consists of personal and professional documents of Carroll's, including: his work at other non-profit organizations, such as the Muslim Consultative Network (MCN), New York Disaster Interfaith Service (NYDIS), Turning Point, Burma Task Force, among others; various side projects and advocacy work that he or others performed; guides and reports; flyers and documents from various events; photographs; and items from his childhood and teenage years, such as personal education documents and performance programs.
Series III. Publications: The series consists of various newspapers, bulletins, newsletters, and magazines, mostly from the Islamic press. Of specific note is Muslims Weekly and the Weekly Mirror, two publications in which Carroll wrote a column and of which exist a large number of volumes in this collection.
Series IV. Audiovisual: The series consists of audiocassette, videocassette, and compact discs, mostly covering different topics pertaining to Islam or religion. Many of the videocassettes include reports and documentaries on the detainees and detention centers. The digital files include non-commercial recordings of a conference, reports on Hurricane Katrina, and some work on detainees.
Series V. Artifacts: The series includes a small amount of physical objects, including a patch from the Bosnian army, a tile with Arabic script, and a certificate.
Audiocassettes.; Compact discs.; Digital media.; Financial documents.; Legal files.; Letters (correspondence); Advocacy, Human rights; Human rights; Islam; Muslims; Muslim Americans; Prisoners; Prisoners -- New York (State).; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Anniversaries, etc.; September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Social aspects.; Terrorism -- New York (State) -- New York.; Victims of terrorism -- New York (State) -- New York.; War on Terrorism, 2001-; United States -- Emigration and immigration.; Islamic Circle of North America; Muslim Community Network
- Series I. Detainee Files, 1998-2011
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains documents pertaining to Carroll's work as the 9/11 Relief Project Coordinator for the Islamic Circle of North America (ICNA), specifically legal and financial relief for those detained by the United States government. The bulk of the series consists of case files concerning various detainees, with the remainder relating to the 9/11 Relief Project more generally.
  The detainee case files hold legal records, such as court transcripts and appeals; correspondence with Carroll, lawyers, the detainees, and government officials; newspaper clippings about the cases; statements from the detainees describing their experiences in detention; financial records, such as bills, disbursements, among others. The documents were kept in their original folders, as Carroll had written notes on them.
  The Relief Project general work files consist of a broad array of information pertaining to his work as 9/11 Relief Project Coordinator, such as loose documents about detainees; brochures and pamphlets for events; correspondence with outside organizations and individuals; personal notes and scratch paper; reports on his work; and to-do lists.
  Arrangement
  The series has been arranged by subject matter, with case files first, followed by related files, and closing with the general project work files.
  - Case files A (10 folders), 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-10)
  - Case files B-Z (10 folders), 1998-2005 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-10)
  - Contacts, 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 11)
  - Detainee lists (2 folders), 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - General correspondence, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 14)
  - Intake forms, 2003 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 15)
  - Legal documents (2 folders), 2002-2003 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Statements from major detainees, 2001-2011 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 3)
  - Relief Project work files (6 folders), 2002-2006 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 4-9)
- Series II. Subject Files, 1964-2018
  The series includes all other elements of Carroll's professional and personal life outside of his work with detainees. As such, the series includes his work with other affiliated non-profits, such as the Burma Task Force, the New York Disaster Interfaith Service (NYDIS), Turning Point, and most notably Muslim Consultative Network (MCN), the organization which he founded and led for several years. These files typically contain mostly internal documents, such as correspondence about various projects, meeting and committee minutes, flyers for events, and Carroll's handwritten planning notes.
  Most other files relate to Carroll's personal life, such as his education documents, photographs of his father and of various events he attended, events and program documents, personal correspondence, and guides and reports. Many of these documents pertain to Islam.
  The content of the series was compiled by the processing archivist from various materials in the collection. The series has been arranged alphabetically by subject matter.
  - Burma Task Force documents, 2016-2017 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 10)
  - Community discussions, 2000-2016 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 11)
    The file includes correspondence, documents, and promotional material about various community conversations and forums (typically co-hosted with a governmental organization, such as the New York Police Department) about 9/11, Islam, tolerance, and human rights. Activist Linda Sarsour is a correspondent in this file.
  - Conferences, 2004-2009 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 12)
  - Council on American-Islamic Relations reports, 2005-2007 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 13)
  - Education correspondence, 2007-2010 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 14)
  - Event flyers and programs (2 folders), 1990-2011 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - Events - various material, 1995-2015 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 17)
    Includes correspondence, programs, handwritten notes, printed news articles, and flyers for various events during the time period.
  - Five Years Beyond 9/11 documents, 2006 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 18)
    Includes documents and correspondence for events in commemoration of the 5th anniversary of 9/11 from various religious organizations, predominately Muslim or interfaith.
  - Guides - educational, 2001, 2005 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 19)
    Holds:
    1. "Crisis Response Guide Human Rights Education Program for Junior and High Schools," Amnesty International, October 2001.
    2. "Guidelines to Best Practices of Islamic Centers," ISNA Leadership Development Center, 2005.
  - Guides - legal, 2002 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 20)
    1. "Special Registration Training Materials," New York Immigration Coalition, 2002.
    2. "A Legal Guide for INS Detainees," American Bar Association, undated.
  - ICNA work files, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 21)
    Primarily covers Carroll's work pertaining to projects other than detainees, including the victims and missing persons during 9/11, grant proposals, and scattered correspondence.
  - Islamic art brochures, 2008-2012 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 22)
  - Islamic art and architecture photographs, Undated (Offsite-box 3, Folder 23)
  - Islamic teaching and education documents, 1994-2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1)
  - MCN 15th anniversary celebration, 2015 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 2)
  - MCN correspondence, 2006-2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 3)
  - MCN governing documents, 2004 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 4)
  - MCN internal documents (2 folders), 2003-2013 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - MCN partnerships, 2009-2010 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 7)
  - New York Disaster Interfaith Services (NYDIS) internal documents, 2001-2003 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 8)
  - North African study, 2000-2002 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 9)
  - Personal education documents, 1973-1989 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, 2005-2006 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 11)
    Includes 17 photographs of people at events, including the Muslim Day Parade, a Darfur rally, and MCN or ISNA tables. Includes photographs with Keith Ellison.
  - Playbills and performance programs, 1971-1976 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 12)
  - Proposals for detainee book project, 2001-2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 13)
  - Ramadan documents and photographs, 2001-2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 14)
  - Raymond Carroll, 1964-1973 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 15)
    Includes invites to and photographs of Raymond Carroll, the subject's father and an editor of Newsweek Magazine. One photo includes then UN Secretary General, Kurt Waldheim, sitting with the elder Carroll.
  - Response to 9/11, 2001 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 16)
  - Responses to smears, 2001-2005 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 17)
  - Various advocacy work and projects, 1985-2007 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 18)
    Includes a notepad of the family members of Muslims killed on 9/11, lists of free legal services, reading lists, Muslim Student Association (MSA) lists, a New York Disaster Interfaith Services (NYDIS) report, assorted correspondence about interfaith work, and newspaper clippings.
  - Various advocacy work and projects, 1995-2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 19)
    Includes brochures and documents pertaining to health and wellness, specifically around H1N1: a research proposal to the Pew Charitable Trust on religion and immigration; a report on religion and education in New York City public schools; correspondence with various consulates about people killed on 9/11; and work reports from ICNA and MCN.
  - Various advocacy work and projects, 2005-2013 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 20)
    Includes documents from various nonprofits Carroll worked with, primarily the NYDIS, Turning Point, and smaller ethnic organizations.
  - Various advocacy work and projects, 2006-2017 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 21)
    Includes political documents and campaign material for Mohammed Razvi; issues from local New York newspapers and clippings; documents and flyers for Darfur rallies; documents pertaining to the Ahmadiyya Muslim community; and scattered correspondence.
  - Various reports, 2001 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 22)
    Two copies of Amnesty International, "United States of America, Memorandum to the US Attorney General - Amnesty International's concerns relating to the post 11 September investigations," November 2001.
  - Various reports, 2002-2005 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 23)
    1. "Report on Hate Crimes and Discrimination Against Arab Americans," American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee Research Institute, October 2002.
    2. Brian Lonergan, "Immigration Detention and Removal: A Guide for Detainees and Their Families," Immigration Law Unit of the Legal Aid Society, October 2004.
    3. "Worlds Apart: How Deporting Immigrants After 9/11 Tore Families Apart and Shattered Communities," ACLU, December 2004.
    4. "Witness to Abuse: Human Rights Abuses under the Material Witness Law since September 11," Human Rights Watch / ACLU, June 2005.
  - Various reports, 2007-2009 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 24)
    1. New York Disaster Interfaith Services Annual Report, 2007.
    2. "Radicalization in the West: The Homegrown Threat," New York Police Department (NYPD), 2007.
    3. "Collateral Damage: How the War on Terror Hurts Charities, Foundations, and the People They Serve," OMB Watch and Grantmakers Without Borders, July 2008.
    4. "US Detention of Asylum Seekers: Seeking Protection, Finding Pirson," Human Rights First, 2009 5. "Unreasonable Intrusions: Invesigating the Politics, Faith, and Finances of Americans Returning Home," Muslim Advocates, April 2009.
    6. "Targeted and Entrapped: Manufacturing the Homegrown Threat in the United States," Center for Human Rights and Global Justice, New York University School of Law, 2011.
  - Various reports, 2011 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 25)
    Includes copy of "Arab and Muslim American Civil Rights and Identity: A Selection of Scholarly Writings from the Decade after 9/11,' American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee Research Institute.
- Series III. Publications, 1988-2010
  The series consists of multiple publications, most of which are newspapers, bulletins, newsletters, and magazines from the Islamic press. Of note are Muslims Weekly and the Weekly Mirror, two Muslim newspapers in which Carroll wrote a column on various aspects of his Muslim faith, spirituality, and current events. There also exists a smaller cache of independent press, as well as sections of larger, international papers such as the New York Times or Le Monde.
  The series has been arranged alphabetically by publication name.
  - Al Dawah Magazine, 2004 June (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1)
    One issue: No. 32
  - CEO International Strategies, 1993 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 2)
    Includes one issue: vol. VI, no. I
  - Fellowship Magazine, 2005-2014 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 3)
    Three issues: vol. 71, no. 9-10 (September/October 2005), vol. 74, no. 1-3 (Spring 2008), vol. 78, no. 1-3 (Spring 2014)
  - The Fountain Magazine, 2010 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 4)
    One issue: no. 75
  - Harper's Magazine, 1999-2003 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 5)
    Two issues: vol. 299, no. 1793 (October 1999); vol. 307, no. 1839 (August 2003)
  - Helping Hand, 2003-2005 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 6)
    ICNA's newsletter to members and employees. Includes 5 issues: vol. 3 (2003), 3 copies of vol. 4 (2004), and vol. 5.1 (2005)
  - The Indypendent, 2004 March (Offsite-box 11)
    Includes 1 issue, no. 46
  - Iqra, 2009 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 7)
    Includes one issue: April/June 2009
  - Islamica Magazine, 2005 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 8)
    Includes one issue: no. 12 (Spring 2005)
  - Lyndon LaRouche campaign magazine, 2004 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 9)
  - The Message International, 2000-2009 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 10)
    Includes 10 issues:
    * Vol. 24, no. 7 (July 2000)
    * Vol. 27, no. 8/9 (August-September 2002)
    * Vol. 29, no. 12/1 (December-January 2004), 2 copies
    * unnumbered (October-November 2005)
    * unnumbered (July-August 2006)
    * unnumbered (January-February 2008)
    * unnumbered (February-March 2009)
    * unnumbered (August-September 2009)
    * unnumbered (November-December 2009).
  - Le Monde, 2004 June (Offsite-box 11)
    Includes one issue, no. 18468
  - Muslim Perspectives, 2004 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 11)
  - Muslims Weekly, 2002 December - 2003 December (Offsite-box 7)
    Includes approximately 40 issues with varying runs: vol. 4 no. 144, vol. 5 no. 161-191.
  - Muslims Weekly, 2004 January - June (Offsite-box 8)
    Includes approximately 40 issues, vol. 6 no. 200-225
  - Muslims Weekly, 2004 July - December (Offsite-box 9)
    Approximately 40 issues, vol. 6 no. 226-252
  - Muslims Weekly, 2005 January - November (Offsite-box 10)
    Includes approximately 30 issues of varying runs, mostly: vol. 7 no. 253-274.
  - New York Review of Books, 2003 September - October (Offsite-box 11)
    Three issues: September 25, 2003 (Vol. L No. 14) - October 23, 2003 (Vol. L, No. 16)
  - New York Times, 2003 May - 2005 April (Offsite-box 11)
    Sections from 3 separate issues, including: 23 May 2003; 20 October 2004; and 11 April 2005
  - New York University Review of Law and Security, 2008 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 12)
    Includes 2 issues: no. 8/9-10 (2008)
  - The Onion, 2003 June (Offsite-box 11)
    2 copies, vol. 39 no. 23
  - Q News, 2002 September (Offsite-box 5, Folder 13)
    Includes 1 issue: no. 347 (September 2002)
  - South Asian Insider, 2004 March (Offsite-box 11)
    Includes 1 issue, vol. 2 no. 52
  - Sufi, 1988-1993 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 14)
    Includes 3 issues: no. 1 (Winter 1988-1989), no. 2 (Spring 1989), no. 8 (Winter 1990-91), no. 19 (Autumn 1993)
  - TransState Islam, 1995 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 15)
    Includes 1 issue: vol. 1, no. 1
  - The Tri-State Muslim, 2008-2009 (Offsite-box 11)
  - Various publications, 1991-2007 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 16)
    Includes an assortment of small, independent newsletters, largely from the Islamic press. There are also some larger titles, like the New York Post. Titles include:
    1. Light for Humanity (April 1996)
    2. Qalbi (May 1993)
    3. New York Post (11 August 2007)
    4. The Voice of Help (January/February 1990)
    5. Fikr (September)
    6. JMIC Newsletter (March-August 1993)
    7. Islam Report (March-April 1994)
    8. Insight (1995)
    9. Rights (Winter 1994)
    10. Muslim News (15 December 1995)
    11. Hudaa Guidance (October 1993)
    12. The Islamic Emirate (July 1995)
    13. The Message International (November-December 2007)
    14. A Piece of Leaf Poetry and Literature (March 1996)
  - Weekly Mirror, 2002 February - 2007 June (Offsite-box 11)
    Approximately 60 volumes of a weekly Muslim newspaper, which features Carroll's weekly column "Between East and West: Reflections from an American Muslim" on page 11. Scattered issues from volumes 1, 2, 6, and 7, while the fullest run exists with vol. 5 no. 220-245.
- Series IV. Audiovisual, 2002-2015
  The series consists of audiocasettes, videocasettes, compact discs, and digital files of various media, mostly pertaining to 9/11 and post-9/11 detentions, as well as educational material about Islam and Islamic holidays.
  The series is organized into two subseries:
  Series IV.A. Digital Formats, 2002-2015
  Series IV.B. Cassette Tapes, 2002-2003
  - Series IV.A. Digital Formats, 2002-2015
    The subseries contains 10 compact discs (8 audio, 2 audiovisual) and the 4.52 gigabytes of digital files preserved from the 10 CDs; and 6 commercial compact discs that Carroll possessed. The topic of these media largely cover 9/11 and post-9/11 detentions, as well as various elements of Islamic culture and religion, Hurricane Katrina, and the use of torture by the United States federal government. The 6 commercial CDs have not been digitally preserved.
    The subseries has been arranged with the CD/DVDs with preserved digital files available for access first, followed by the restricted digital media.
    - 10 CDs (RESTRICTED), 2002-2008 (Offsite-box 6, Disk 1-10)
    - [1] Under Attack: Arab, Muslim and South Asian Communities Since September 11, 2004 (Digital folder MS 3212)
      Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
      WAV audio file; 29 minutes.
    - [2] The Justice Department's Detention Secret, 2002 September (Digital folder MS 3212)
    - [3-4] Katrina: Where Do We Go From Here? Parts 1-2, 2005 December (Digital folder MS 3212)
      Part 1: MP4 video file; 1 hour. Part 2: MP4 video file; 1 hour, 24 minutes.
    - [5-10] Religion and Violence: Untangling the Roots of Conflict Conference, 2008 January (Digital folder MS 3212)
      Titles include:
      1. Katharine Jefferts Schori, Opening Sermon (WAV audio file; 14 minutes)
      2. Tarqi Ramadan, "God's Design: Our Common Responsibility Towards the Future" (WAV audio file; 54 minutes)
      3. James H. Cone, "God and Black Suffering: Calling the Oppressors to Account" (WAV audio file; 1 hour)